The Arclight project.
How to exclude eye disease when dispensing eyeglasses?
When dispensing eyeglasses it is important to exclude other underlying eye disease.
With a visual acuity chart and an Arclight device you can quickly find out who needs
glasses and what type and who may need referral for other diseases such as cataracts and
glaucoma.
Start with distance visual acuity testing one eye at a time unaided and if reduced use a pinhole.
then test near vision with both eyes together.
There are typically five possible outcomes.
If the distance in near visual acuity are both good,
the patient does not need glasses.
If the distance vision is reduced,
but improves with the pinhole and the near vision is okay,
then the patient is most slightly short-sighted, also known as myopic.
If the distance vision is reduced but improves with the pinhole,
and the near vision is also reduced,
then the patient is most likely a long sighted,
also known as hyperopia.
If the distance vision is okay,
but the near vision is reduced,
and the patient is over 40 years of age,
then they have pressed biopia and need reading glasses.
Finally, if visual acuity is reduced
and does not improve with pinhole or glasses,
then underlying eye disease is very likely,
patient needs examination with the arc light.
Move to a dimly lit room and start with a direct
pupil light reflex.
Both people should constrict equally and briskly to light.
If they do not
constrict well, there is likely to be disease of the optic nerve or retina
at the back of
the eye, such as glaucoma or retinal detachment.
Next check the fundal reflex test.
A bright symmetric reflex means there is nothing blocking
the light entering the eye.
If the reflex is reduced or absent, then cataract, corneal
scar, blood in the back of the eye or a tumour, maybe blocking the light.
Next check the front
of the eye, close up with the anterior segment loop.
Look for any corneal infection and scarring
or cataract.
Finally, perform direct optomoscopy and look into the back of the eye.
Xammon optic
nerve and retina for signs of glaucoma, thyroid retinopathy, scarring and retinal
detachment.
If any disease is present or you still can't work out why the
patient's vision is pure, then make a plan for the patient to see an eye specialist.
This video demonstrates that through practice with regular mentorship,
general healthcare workers, even with low-cost tools, can understand if a
patient would benefit from eyeglasses or need referral for treatment of underlying
disease.
A powerful process with one low cost tool anywhere in the world by
anyone.